[Music]
[Applause]
from the heart of
Orlando
Florida you are listening to the most
electrifying show in media a neighbor's
choice and I'm your host your neighbor
David groski so glad you could join me
today in my beautiful neighborhood here
in Central Florida and we have a lot to
cover today because we are at the heart
of what is going on with the
controversies in regards to what they
have been calling the you know the
Russian collusion uh investigation
that's going to be breaking tomorrow
morning and a lot of people want to know
what is that all about what is in the
Mueller
report from the cliffnotes version We
Know according to attorney general bar
that there was not anything there as we
had already most of us had already
understood to be there there was nothing
there but we're going to see now the
details so there's a lot of people on
the left who are looking to this Mueller
report like it's the coming of the Ten
Commandments we will finally see the
sacred document that gives millions of
people their sense of meaning and
purpose and
togetherness and that's the nature of
the hallucinatory aspect of modern media
is that there's this kind of desire to
always have a scapegoat to always have a
foreign Boogeyman or an internal
Boogeyman
and the perfect scapegoats are the ones
that have both an internal aspect and an
external aspect one foot in on the
inside crowd and one foot on the outside
crowd and in that case Trump is a
perfect candidate for a scapegoat
because he's both the consumate you know
businessman in New York City uh you know
so he's an Insider but then he's got you
know International interests and so if
you can tar someone like that and say
well you know you thought you knew this
man but in reality he's crooked he's a
casino Mogul and that's why we should
suspect that he might have had something
to do with the Russian government well
then he's a classic perfect case for a
scapegoat and so it'll be interesting to
see what the the details are I think
that $35 million Mueller spent with
highly
conflicted uh many often times people
that had worked uh on the law firms for
the CL Clint Foundation this is
ridiculous it's a joke and uh and yet
still so much of the alleged Free Press
will tell you that no it was there was
nothing conflicted about that that's
just some kind of right-wing blog that
says there was a conflict of interest
with the people
investigating uh the Trump uh Russia
question but still we'll wait for the
details tomorrow morning but in the
meantime I'm excited about my guest here
because he is someone who has actually
interacted on a personal level with some
of the people involved in the uh Russia
collusion investigation for Trump he's a
a former CIA agent his name is John
kiraku welcome to the program how you
doing thanks so much for having me doing
well thanks yeah and I I've I've read
about your story and i' I I was able to
uh you know kind of dive into some of
the details and I'm I'm fascinated for a
lot of topics that I think you can
provide insights in uh you're a
whistleblower you're someone who uh you
came out and you went on uh television
and you let the world know that indeed
there was uh torture taking place in the
CIA and uh you ended up serving time for
that isn't that correct that's true yes
um I went on ABC News in December of
2007 and I said that uh the CIA was
torturing its prisoners that torture was
official US government policy it was not
the result of a rogue as the president
president had intimated and I said that
the um that the policy had been
personally approved by the president and
as you might imagine the CIA didn't take
well to that now what led you to reveal
this I mean what was going on in your
mind when you decided to reveal this
well a couple of things uh first of all
I am a I am a strong strong believer in
the Constitution of the United States I
believe in the rule of law reasonable
people can agree to disagree on policy
but if you don't like the policy that
you have to change the law uh you can't
just pretend that the law doesn't exist
and uh you know we have an anti-torture
law in this country I'm not just talking
about the McCain Feinstein amendment of
2015 we've got an anti-torture law that
dates back to
1946 and we're also signatories and not
just signatories but we were the
drafters of the United Nations
convention Against torture and so I
believed that it was my duty as a CIA
officer to uh blow the on what I believe
to be waste fraud abuse and illegality
and so that's what I did how many years
did you spend in the CIA and other you
know Intel agencies uh I was in the CIA
for 15 years and most of that was as a
counterterrorism operations officer now
you were the head of counterterrorism
for the CIA for in Pakistan correct
correct in the immediate aftermath of
the 911 attacks I headed
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
can you give a Layman some insight here
why do we give billions of dollars to
Pakistan and allow them to have nukes
and yet was Osama bin Laden was he just
a few miles away from their main base is
that right uh yeah AMA Bin Laden was
actually living in the Pakistani version
of West Point uh and you ask a very
important and very good question it's
really The $64,000 Question why do we
give Pakistan uh billions and billions
of dollars in economic and military aid
when they are a nuclear power in
violation of the nonproliferation treaty
and um and are constantly on the brink
of war with India which is an important
us trading partner uh and the truth is
that the policy is very complicated and
we just prefer to pretend that these
problems don't exist so is it like duck
duck goose we just kind of duck duck
goose okay you're the guys we're going
to give nukes to everybody else we're
going to sanction to destroy and make
everybody think that they're like the
worst place in the world is that how it
works welome to Washington because
that's exactly how this City Works uh
you know it's funny you you have a
policy and you would think that because
you have a policy you stick with it the
truth is that there's an exception to
every policy and so there's always a
quid proquo we go to the pakistanis and
we say if you do a b and c for us we're
going to pretend that you don't have
nuclear weapons and they say that sounds
like a good deal to us and then we all
just play this game wow you know I I
just don't understand so is did did
Pakistan do they do they um do they kind
of work with the Petr dollar system and
everything and that's why they uh you
know Persona n grada versus Iran you
know cuz I know Iran doesn't play ball
uh when it comes to our oil interest and
so forth is that a good is that a good
uh quick and dirty cheat sheet for why
those guys have nukes and we're supposed
to be told every night that you know
that's nothing to see here in Pakistan
but go ahead and and and uh let's vilify
and Destroy Iran right I I think no I
think the real reason is that the
pakistanis are perfectly willing to
kneel down before us when we want them
to for example U the pakistanis share a
border with China and in fact they're
very close to the Chinese politically
but if we want access to the Chinese
border maybe we want to put a listening
post up there they say go ahead and have
at it we need um access to uh to the
border with Iran in the south of
Pakistan that's an area called
beluchistan where we have our our drone
base they say have at it we tell them we
need a staging area to go to go into
Afghanistan they welcome us and give us
uh a base for it and then at the same
time uh they come to us and say look
we've done all these things for you
we've given you these bases we let you
spy on the Chinese and the Iranians and
the Afghans and and whomever else we
want to spy on so what you're going to
do for us is you're going to look the
other way while we build this nuclear
weapon and also you're going to look the
other way as we arm these Kashmir
separatists and Kashmir terrorists who
are going to attack the Marriott in
Mumbai
and uh and attack the the Mumbai Jewish
center and and kill uh kill Jews there
and so uh we do we look the other way
and then when push comes to shove we
point the finger at Al-Qaeda and we
pretend that the Pakistani government
had nothing to do with it so wait a
second our Geniuses in DC they're giving
billions of dollars to these guys they
have this deep connection relationship
and they didn't know that Osama Bin
Laden was in their West Point their
equivalent of West Point over
there you know that's uh that uh
stretches um credulity doesn't it so um
I I was always of the opinion that the
pakistanis knew that Osama Bin Laden was
there you have to be you have to be a
mental defective to not know Osama Bin
Laden was there everybody knew that he
wasn't in some cave in Afghanistan that
he was probably in one of the major
cities because all of the other Al-Qaeda
Fighters that we had caught and Al-Qaeda
leaders that we had caught were in
Pakistan's major cities we caught khed
shik Muhammad in ra pin
we caught Ramsey Ben aib in in Karachi
we caught uh we caught Omar Al baluch in
in karach these guys are in big cities
they're in safe houses they're in
they're in apartments they're not in
caves anywhere and so we in the CIA
always assumed he was living comfortably
somewhere in Pakistan and and certainly
he was now let me qualify that too by
saying that I worked very very closely
with Pakistani intelligence uh Services
when I was when I was living there and
assigned there and I was always of the
opinion that there were two parallel
Pakistani intelligence Services there
were the counterterrorism guys that I
worked with who were educated in the UK
or in the US and they loved us and they
would lay down their lives for us and
then there were the other guys in their
headquarters with the long bushy beards
who had come of age in Afghanistan who
created the Taliban who would give you
the stink eye whenever you'd go over to
their their headquarters for me meetings
and it's like these two sides of the
same organization were working against
each other and working against us at the
same time wow whoa and that makes my
head that makes my head so so so it's
almost like if you PID it was it kind of
like a pay for playay like look if if
you give us $2 billion do in Aid you get
this and then if you want to chip in
another billion America will let you
know what's under door number one where
there's Osama Bin Laden right next door
West it's like you know what that's
that's a really good way to put it and
and the short answer is yes that's
exactly what it is we're going to take a
quick commercial break we're with John
kiraku former CIA agent and you're
listening to a neighbor's Choice with
David groski don't go anywhere more on
the other
side oh c where you going to run
[Music]
hi I'm David
groski and welcome back to a neighbors
Choice
radio I'm your political Exorcist I'm
here to cast out all of the negative
spirits of group think in our lives and
reclaim our country neighbor to neighbor
for the message of nonviolence peace
love and working together all grounded
in the principles of personhood the idea
that the individual person is at the
fulcrum of everything that matters in
terms of our law and what we should
allow in our own Civic society and I'm
joined right now by a very fascinating
guest his name is John kiraku he's a
former CIA agent he was the head of the
counterterrorism unit for them in
Pakistan during the height of a lot of
the things going on over there um and he
became a whistleblower he decided that
he had seen evidence of ter uh torture
and he did not believe that that was an
ethical thing for him to be a part of
and he decided to speak out about it did
you actually see the activity yourself
or you just knew about it through the
the the system or whatever no I I did
not see it myself what happened was when
I finished my tour in Pakistan I
returned to CIA headquarters in Langley
Virginia and I was in the cafeteria one
day and a senior officer uh with whom I
worked came up to me and very casually
said hey I'm glad I ran into you I
wanted to ask do you want to be
certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques I had never
heard that term before this was May the
6th of 2002 and I said enhanced
interrogation techniques what's that
mean and he described these 10
techniques and I said ooh that sounds
like a torture program and he said no
it's not torture we got it approved by
the White House we got it approved by
the National Security Council the
justice Department I said I don't know
man that sounds like torture and torture
is a slippery slope I don't think I want
to be involved with that as it turned
out they had asked 14 um of us uh
operations officers and I was the only
one who said no I'm I'm very sorry to
say and so on the strength of the work
that I did in Pakistan we had we had
captured Abu zubeda who we believed at
the time was the number three in alqaeda
um I got promoted and I became the
executive assistant to the cia's deputy
director and so in that position I had
access to literally every um operation
that the CIA was running around the
world it's a very unusual position and
so as soon as they began torturing abua
and others I was the recipient of the
cables coming back from the secret sites
the secret prisons and um and you know
even inside the the agency we were
fooled because the reporting was being
done by two contract psychologists
uh Mitchell and jessen who were
reporting that that the uh torture was
was actually successful and that Abu
Zeda was was giving us information that
was saving American lives and disrupting
attacks that turned out to be a lie what
they had done was that they copied
information that Abu zua had freely
given the FBI and because the FBI
computer system and the CIA computer
system had no connectivity we and the
CIA didn't know that the that the had
already been reported to the FBI and
Mitchell and Jess were lying and saying
that they had collected it we didn't
know that until
2009 and so um we were getting this
reporting back saying everything is
copasetic he cracked he broke he cried
he he wet himself he gave us all this
information uh we accidentally made his
heart stop we had to revive him and and
it was just uh it was torture for
nothing it was a violation of the law it
was a violation of the Constitution and
uh and it resulted in nothing nothing
but but a black eye for for our country
so what would make them want to lie
about it I mean what if they just I mean
because because they they were already
Under Fire about it internally or
something I can tell you exactly what
made them lie uh they had signed a $18
million
contract and so they had to make sure
that everybody in headquarters in a
position to have oversight over that
contract believed that the that the
techniques were working because they
wanted to collect that $108 million what
did they need that money for what was
that going to into their pockets for
what what to do well that's how that's
how Mitchell and Jess got rich they had
this uh this organization Mitchell and
jessen Associates and what they did is
they reverse engineered the uh Air Force
sear program that's that's the program
where we teach our Pilots um how to
withstand uh torture if they're shot
down Behind Enemy Lines they RSE
engineered it and they used it to create
an offensive torture program promising
the cia's leadership that it would work
and that it would disrupt the tax and so
we gave them $108 million because they
had made these promises and by God they
were going to make sure that we believed
that the that the program was working so
water boarding as a technique not that
they invented it but water boarding was
something sold to the CIA from a private
contractor
correct that was their thing whoa I I
always just had the you know the P you
know I always just thought like it was
just some kind of technique that they
had in their back pocket from the
medieval times they like hey let's pull
this out that'll get it to work that's
where it originated it originated in
medieval China oh wow and and was used
as recently as the Vietnam War I mean
you go through history and it was used
by the belgians in the Congo it was it
was used in medieval China it was used
uh my God during the second world war
and and I'll tell you something this is
this is one of the things that that
really made me decide to go public in
1946 we executed Japanese soldiers who
had waterboarded American PS We executed
them this was a death penalty offense in
January of
1968 The Washington Post ran a front
page photograph of an American Soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner on the same day that that photo
ran the Secretary of Defense Robert S
mcamera ordered an investigation that
Soldier was arrested he was charged with
torture he was convicted and sentenced
to 20 years at hard labor in lenworth
well the law never changed we changed so
in 1946 this was a death penalty act in
1968 it was worth 20 years at hard labor
but somehow in 2002 it was magically
patriotic and perfectly legal to do when
the law didn't change
that made no sense to me and the
justification of course was that 911
happened and therefore all stops had to
be you know throwing out the window all
breaks exactly I remember George tenant
saying that Osama Bin Laden had promised
that he was planning another attack that
would dwarf 911 and George was panicked
at the notion that there would be two
such attacks on his watch and that's why
he was willing to do literally anything
to stop the next attack including giving
Mitchell and Jess $108 million to
torture people why didn't why do they
have to pay a contractor to do it why
couldn't they they just you know hire a
consultant to teach the CIA agents how
to do
it well you know that's kind of been an
an ongoing debate why why did they bring
in Outsiders to do it and there are a
couple of theories although none of the
principles have ever really said um you
I remember meeting Mitchell and jessen
in CIA headquarters in October of 2001
just after the attacks and the reason
they came to my attention is that
there's a rule at the CIA that
contractors are not allowed to have
private offices but these guys got
private offices and I I remember saying
uh hey who are the stiffs over there
moving into the private offices oh I
don't know they must be somebody because
they're contractors they have green
badges instead of blue badges so they
got private offices they must be big
shots well there were a couple of
different theories as to why they were
hired
one of the theories is that they had uh
some kind of contact with the deputy
director for Science and Technology who
introduced them to the head of
counterterrorism and they were ready to
go so the CIA wouldn't have to reinvent
the wheel and start creating this
program from scratch they had already
done it and they were ready to implement
it right then and there the other uh
theory is that this way you weren't
putting CIA officers in direct danger
these contract contractors were people
who had decided this is what they wanted
to do and they were doing it for money
not for any other reason and so if there
was going to be legal Fallout they can
handle their own dog on legal Fallout
and there wouldn't be a congressional
investigation that would end up pointing
the finger at CIA
officers interesting we're speaking with
John kiraku who's former CIA agent who
was involved with uh he became a
whistleblower that really revealed a lot
of what was going on with the torture
programs that we were told were not
torture but let's kind of Whittle this
down um why did they choose the
waterboarding technique as their
favorite torture technique that's a
great question that's a great question
and the rules were very clear that they
were not supposed to begin with water
boarding water boarding was supposed to
be the the final punishment right if you
couldn't get any uh information using
any other technique at the very end you
should go to water boarding well
Mitchell and jesson were so excited to
see the implementation of their program
that they began with water boarding and
there were other things that they did
too that were that were patently illegal
what did they do they get like a bonus
every time they waterboarded or
something is this like a sales
commission they got the ability to write
a cable to headquarters saying oh we we
did X Y and Z and we waterboarded him
and he was frothing at the mouth and his
heart stopped and he was crying and
begging and and all of which was true
and it made them look like true tough
guys where do they find these guys at
are they like hiding in a Siberian
Tundra Wilderness like they just work
pretty much uh they were hiding at a
university in Eastern Washington State
oh Lord I would want to drink their
water my goodness so what in the world
it's just hard to wrap my mind around
this so so then so they pick this
waterboarding technique right and they
they they just flip through like a
medieval torture manuscript from China
and just like a scroll unrolled it and
say what that looks really nasty let's
try this one essentially yes that's
that's basically what they did but there
were other things too and there were
actually techniques that I always
believed were worse than water boarding
one was um very easy it was sleep
deprivation you know how hard it is to
stay awake well the American
Psychological Association tells us that
people begin to lose their minds at day
seven with no sleep they begin to die at
day nine right but Mitchell and jessen
were authorized to keep prisoners awake
for up to 12 days and what what they
ended up doing was um was so harming
people with sleep deprivation that they
actually did lose their minds and
they're unable to participate in their
own defenses wow so here these guys are
at Guantanamo they're certifiably insane
because of this this experience and
they're unable to assist their own
attorneys defending them so I always
thought that was worse than
waterboarding waterboarding at least
wasn't permanent other than when your
heart stopped beating and the other one
was uh called the cold cell that is
where the prisoner was stripped naked he
was chained to an eyebolt in the ceiling
so that he couldn't sit or or lay down
or get comfortable in any way his cell
was chilled to 30 degrees I'm sorry it
was chilled to 50 Dees Fahrenheit and
then every hour um a CIA officer would
go into the cell and throw a bucket of
ice water on him and we actually killed
two prisoners doing that we killed them
uh with
hypothermia they uh essentially froze to
death I know there was a popular thought
that the water boarding cannot kill you
is that true uh no it can kill you
because water actually does get down the
windpipe and um and you can drown you
can drown with just a little bit of
water the thing is is they had CIA
Physicians there observing the water
boarding we used to jokingly yeah well
was kind of dark humor but jokingly call
them call them Dr mangala so you have Dr
mangala uh sitting by every time Abu
zeta's heart would stop beating he would
revive him they'd give him a day to
recover and then they'd waterboard him
again what happened to this this
individual what what I don't know his
story Zab he was um transferred from one
secret prison to another he ended up
going to four or five different secret
prisons around the world and in uh
2005 he was transferred to Guantanamo
and he's been there ever since held in
communicado and we know from the uh
Senate torture report that um he will
never be released ever under any
circumstances and that in the event of
his death he is to be cremated and his
ashes scattered into the sea wow so they
don't want no one to he's he's in a uh a
chamber of of no of no anything he can't
communicate and let me add the postcript
to that as it turns out abua was not the
number three in al-Qaeda our information
was wrong this was the wrong guy a
different is those like two of the same
names he and a first cousin had exactly
the same oh are you Ser wait a second
this is just his cousin yeah see this
was the topic of my third book um I was
tell us the name of the book by the way
so we can keep it oh sure it's it's
called uh
um oh my god I've written so many books
I can't think of the title now it's
called the convenient terrorist abuaba
and the weird Wonderland of America's
Secret Wars um yeah
abua hold that thought we're going to
take a quick commercial break we're
speaking with John kiraku CIA
whistleblower and this is fascinating
stuff don't go anywhere folks we're
learning what's going on on a
neighbors's choice radio I'm David
groski don't go anywhere
[Music]
welcome back to a neighbors Choice radio
I'm David granoski I'm speaking with
John kiraku who is a CIA whistleblower
he's now on the outside but he had a
decorated career in there before he saw
what was going on with their torture
behavior and activity and decided to
speak out and he paid for it and we're
going to get into that in just a moment
but I just wanted to follow up you said
that they you know they this target of
this waterboarding and other torture
practices Abu zabada was the wrong guy
the wrong Abu yeah the the Abu Zaba that
we caught was certainly a bad guy he he
U ran what was called the house of
Martyrs uh training facility and safe
house in pesha Pakistan but he never
joined Al-Qaeda and he never pledged uh
loyalty or fty to AMA Bin Laden there
was a cousin a first cousin with the
same name Abu zubeda and he was actually
um in and out of the United States well
as soon as 9911 happened he assumed
correctly that the FBI and the CIA would
be looking for him and as soon as the
9911 attacks took place he fled to
Jordan and he went underground and we
were never never able to find him but
not knowing that there were two
different guys with the same name oh man
if you're collecting information from
NSA FBI
CIA on both of these guys and you think
it's one guy this looks like a Terri
terrorist Superman right and so we
finally tracked one of the Abu aetas
down to um fisel laad Pakistan and on
the evening of March 22nd 2 2002 we we
busted down the door with battering rams
and we grabbed him and everybody else
inside and the rest is history so
probably I'm just imagining half the
torture was him trying to them trying to
con get him to admit that he was the
right Abu he was like no you've got
absolutely correct you're absolutely
correct and the thing is is it took us
years to realize that we had made this
mistake but by then he had been tortured
he had been exposed to secret prisons he
was in
Guantanamo and now he knows too much and
so he can't be released so here you've
got this guy who has never been charged
with a crime right he's never been
charged with a crime but he'll never go
free and to me that's just not the
American way so
I if there was like okay so he was the
wrong Abu but he he did do some bad
stuff you said so if there was evidence
that he did these bad stuff I mean would
that be I mean obviously I'm not trying
to say that well that warrants what he's
going through but sure sure I mean would
would it be a relatively similar uh uh
stay for what he was if you could pin
the the actual stuff he did do and prove
evidence no no he had never actually
committed a a a terrorist uh attack so
he was involved in training and
logistics for terrorists or of
terrorists yes so if if we had known
that there were two of them and we
caught him he probably would have done a
good 10 years or maybe even 15 years in
prison or in Guantanamo or whatever and
he would have been released by now and
if he had sold marijuana he would have
been in prison for life so that's for
sure oh you're so right so man this is
just this is like a a house a carnival
House of mirrors and and bizaar
uh to just look into this stuff you know
we've made repeated terrible mistakes
that have affected the lives of innocent
people
um was it the case that Osama Bin Laden
denied isn't it true that he denied that
he was involved when it first came out
that that you know when the news of the
911 attacks happened oh no uh he didn't
deny it uh in fact he issued a a video
I'm sorry an audio recording to Al jazer
uh in in the weeks after 9/11 saying
that U that this was punishment for uh
the US his words polluting the land of
the two holy mosques which means having
troops based in Saudi Arabia and um and
this was our punishment and that's when
he said that that he was planning an
attack that would dwarf 911 right no I I
knew he came out eventually and said he
did it but I thought there was like one
statement he made where he's like oh no
I didn't do that then he then he changed
his his his stance on that was that
that's you may be thinking about um
about a statement that came out of uh
the Pentagon right after 911 very
briefly accusing heala of doing it okay
and saying that it wasn't Bin Laden that
it was his Bala and then his Bala which
is and this was really out of character
came out and said whoa we don't like you
guys but we didn't have anything to do
with this
wow so how did it you know if we had
this relationship with Pakistan and you
were the head of counterterrorism there
from what years were you over there in
Pakistan I was there from uh it was a
short tour because um because it was so
dangerous we were cycling in and out so
I was there for uh 7 months
from let's see I was there from January
to May and then again from June to
August of 2002
wow yeah it was it was dangerous I'm
looking here this is an article from
cnn.com Bin Laden says he wasn't behind
the attacks in a statement issued to the
Arabic Satellite Channel Al jazer this
is cnn.com
based in Qatar Bin Laden said the US
government has consistently blamed me
for being behind every occasion its
enemies attack it I would like to assure
the world that I did not plan the recent
attacks which seem to have been planned
by people for personal reasons and he's
been living in the Islamic he said so
this is September 17th 2001 so why did
he deny it at first I don't understand
right you know what I we were we were
doing 24-hour shifts back then and I
must have been just so preoccupied with
finding ter I didn't pay attention to
that isn't that I just it's weird that
he you know he he he denied it at first
you know just you know six days later
and then he changes I guess his tune
shortly after and starts accepting that
so I don't understand that crazy it's
weird but anyways I Funny the funny
thing about Bin Laden too is that he had
literally zero religious credentials he
was just a he was a nobody he was the
son of of one of the wealthiest men in
um in Saudi Arabia ABD Rahman Bin Laden
uh the the family is worth tens of
billions of dollars they're in charge of
uh of all the biggest construction
projects in the Kingdom they build
airports and ports and hospitals he's
kind of like their version of trump over
there even bigger way bigger than Trump
and the old man had 110 Sons so Osama
was one of the younger Sons uh and he
was he was sort of the one that went bad
you know there are probably five dozen
Bin Laden family members who live here
in the United States permanently uh
Beverly Hills a lot of them live in
Miami and uh they wanted nothing to do
with their brother uh they had a rough
time here in the states after the 911
attacks and almost all of them left the
country for a year or two and then just
started to come back by 2003 2004 wow
just fascinating stuff U I want to go on
the other side we're going to take a
quick commercial break in just a minute
here but I wanted to on the other side
kind of go into your thoughts on the
Assan story and kind of unpack that
because you know you're a whistleblower
and you paid uh the price you spent how
many years in prison because of what you
did I was there for 23 months 23 months
we have a lot of people on our program
that call in for nonviolent victimless
crimes they call in from prison uh and
they discuss their experience of what
prison's like so on the other side with
John kiraku I want to ask you what your
experience was like in prison and more
about whistleblowing on the other side
you're listening to a neighbor's Choice
don't go
[Music]
anywhere a neighbor CH radio is back and
I'm your host David groski here with
John kiraku former CIA agent and we're
exploring a lot of fascinating topics
and we're going to have to have John on
again some more to unpack he's a wealth
of knowledge and a part of American
government that a lot of people know
very little of including myself and I
guess that's the way they've designed it
of course it's the CIA but uh you know
we should know what they're doing you
know they're supposed to be our public
servants but you know they're over here
you know taking out Chinese medieval
torture techniques on people and uh got
the wrong guy got the wrong Abu at least
in this case that you've been exploring
on the show with us today um uh so I
wanted to kind of go briefly through you
know we have people uh call in from
prison for non-violent victimless
behaviors and of course so you tell the
truth about the the torture I don't did
you I mean was their argument that you
hurt someone that you that you
endangered someone's life by saying that
no uh what they argued was that the um
was that the information was classified
and so they charged me with three counts
of Espionage if you can imagine such a
thing so how would they have proven that
in court like what would be their CA
what would be their argument what was
their best argument that you were espion
well there's this there's this phrase
when discussing classified information
that it is currently and appropriately
classified um my contention was that you
can't classify a crime it's actually a
crime in the United States to classify
something just because it's a crime or
because it causes embarrassment to the
government um but they they wanted to go
to the mat and and not because they
necessarily wanted a prosecute John
kiraku the point was to frighten any
other wouldbe whistleblower uh from
public so they could say you see what we
did to this guy you want the same thing
to happen to you then you keep your big
mouth shut but my attorneys told me in
the very beginning look this is way
bigger than you this case isn't about
you this case is about freedom of speech
it's about government accountability and
it's about transparency you exposed a
crime you embarrassed them all the way
up to the president and they don't like
to be embarrassed and so we decided to
fight I was going to go to trial and um
I uh I pleaded not guilty I was facing
45 years in prison and um and so my uh
my attorneys received Discovery from the
justice department and we asked the
judge to declassify 70 cables necessary
for me to defend myself to prove that
this was a crime that that the torture
program was a crime and so it was
illegal to make it a classified program
and so the judge uh we blocked off two
days for the hearings and we went into
court and the judge said I'm going to
make this easy for everybody and I'm
going to deny all 70 of these motions my
attorneys flipped out objection
objection objection and then because it
was a national security case um the
prosecution was allowed to ask for
something called A Part 13 conversation
which means an in camera conversation a
private conversation with a judge in her
Chambers without my attorneys present
that's legal only in a national security
case and so the prosecutors went back
there with the judge they were back
there for 20 minutes they came back out
I have no idea what they said about me
back there and the judge looked at me
and she said I'm denying all 70 of these
motions and she looked at me and she
says don't make me take this to
trial well she just underc my whole
defense so I have to go to trial because
the best that the government said they
would do was 10 years in a in a
Penitentiary and I said I'm not going to
do 10 minutes and so I told them that I
was rejecting their 10 years and I was
going to go to trial and I was going to
testify on my own behalf and in that
testimony I may have to find myself
talking about some of the Hideous crimes
against humanity and war crimes that I
witnessed in my 15 years in CIA
counterterrorism that I had to defend
myself and then they came back and they
said okay 23 months well the bottom line
is the government wins 98.2% of its
cases according to propublica so do you
roll the dice knowing that you have a
1.8% chance to win do you take the 23
months or do you gamble and risk getting
18 to 24 years which is what my my
lawyers believed I would get if I had
lost so I took the deal besides that I
had already spent $1.1 million on my
defense it wiped me out I went bankrupt
and I still owe my lawyers $880,000 that
they're never going to
see so as my attorneys told me in the
very beginning this is more than just
about you this is about scaring
everybody else in government who might
be thinking about reporting a
crime well yeah they used you as a
public scapegoat to send a message
message to to that we're angry at the
public and we're going to take it out on
you because you opened up this crisis of
of humiliation and revealing of our sins
and our wickedness in high places and so
that's why they had to make an example
of you so you went to prison for what
two years then yeah two years just sort
of two years did did you receive uh
health effects or PTSD because of the
experience oh you bet I did you know the
funny thing too is that um you know I
was the victim of two assassination
attempts in my career once in Athens and
once in a Middle Eastern country that
I'm not allowed to to discuss and I
didn't have PTSD from two assassination
attempts I didn't have PTSD from
breaking down doors and chasing Al-Qaeda
and Pakistan but boy I had major PTSD
when I got back from prison wow did you
so you had threats of violence against
you and stuff like no um actually uh the
prisoners uh welcomed me they adopted me
especially the Italians uh and when I
say Italian I mean like with air
Italians named Gambino and Lui banano
Etc um and it was because I hate the FBI
as much as they do uh but it was the the
guards it was the guards that were
always after me oh that reminds me of
the Stanford Prison Experiment huh oh
yes so you Liv that experiment oh yes
and I can tell you from firsthand
experience that that experiment was
exactly correct in its findings wow
people become monsters well I'm sorry
you had to go through that just for
being a patriot and trying to keep your
government accountable
we're going to have to have you on again
sometime John kiraku I'm glad you're
with your family now and keep telling
the truth and I know you're in a new
eyeway way documentary so what's the
name of that movie um it's called Uh
yours truly yours truly iway Way's new
movie Yours Truly has John kiraku John
kiraku dcom folks thanks again John
thank you you've been listening to
another episode of a neighbors Choice
radio I'm David groski Godspeed
one day I thought I could
fly one day I woke up and I
could SE
[Music]